Einar...
埃...埃納爾
W... Wait!
等...等等
Wait!
等等...
Damn it!
該死
Why am I here?
我怎麼...會在這裡?
I can't fall.
我不能跌下去
If I fall down there...
如果我跌下去的話...
Please stop!
請...請不要這樣!
Please!
求...求求你
Good morning, Thorfinn.
早安,托爾芬
Seems like your nightmare was worse than usual.
看來你的惡夢似乎比平常更糟糕
In my dream
在我的夢裡
I fell from a cliff.
我跌落了懸崖
- You remember your dream this time? - A little.
-你這次記得你的夢境了? -一點點
You were talking a lot in your sleep.
你在睡夢中一直說夢話
Things like, "Father" and "Askeladd."
像是“爸爸”還有“阿謝拉特”
Is Askeladd someone's name?
阿謝拉特是個人名嗎?
No matter
不管我...
how hard I try,
多麼努力
I can't remember my dream.
我就是記不得我的夢境
All I know is that it's a terrifying dream.
我只知道是個可怕的惡夢
Also...
還有...
I feel...
我感覺...
like I am forgetting something very important.
我似乎忘了某件很重要的事
It's as if I have a small bone
像是有根小骨頭
stuck in my throat.
梗在我的喉嚨
It's terrifying. I want to forget it.
真的很可怕,我想要忘了它
But I feel like it's something I must not forget.
但我又感到我不該忘了那件事
What is it?
到底是什麼?
Look, their wheat has grown this much already.
你看,他們的小麥已經長麼高了
Is it because it's newly cleared land and the soil is fertile?
是因為這是新整出來的耕地 而且土壤很肥沃的關係嗎?
No, it must be Einar.
不是,一定是埃納爾的緣故
Ever since he came, the development has sped up.
自從他來了之後 農作的栽培速度就快了很多
Damn it, the master must be out of his mind.
該死,主人一定是瘋了
Cultivating a field is a job meant for respectable men.
種田是屬於正派人士的工作
Not for wretched slaves.
而不是可憐的奴隸
This is not right.
這樣是不對的
Even if it's the master's orders.
儘管這是主人的命令
If slaves and farmhands are treated equally,
如果奴隸和農場幫手受到同等待遇
it will disrupt the order within society.
這會破壞社會秩序
Don't you agree?
你們不同意嗎?
Askeladd
阿謝拉特...
was the man who killed my father.
他是我的殺父仇人
He was a Dane and a warmonger.
他是丹麥人,而且是好戰份子
He was strong and cruel.
他既強壯又殘忍
- I'll throw it to you. - Okay.
-我丟給你 -好
So he came out in your dream?
他出現在你的夢裡?
I don't know.
我不知道
I followed Askeladd
我追逐著阿謝拉特
onto the battlefield.
一路追上了戰場
In order to avenge my father.
為了替我爸復仇
For ten years...
十年...
No, for eleven years, I fought.
不,我戰鬥了11年
I hated him.
我恨他
Enough to want to kill him.
恨不得殺了他
So, did you get revenge?
你復仇成功了嗎?
No...
沒有
Askeladd was
阿謝拉特...
killed by another man
我眼睜睜地看著他
right in front of my eyes.
死於別人的劍下
Thorfinn, throw me another one.
托爾芬,再丟一梱給我
Okay.
好
There!
接好
Well,
是說...
I don't know about the details,
我不清楚細節
but I feel like
但我覺得
I understand why you're in low spirits now.
我終於能夠體會 為何你的情緒會這麼低落了
The fact that it comes out in your dreams
從他出現在你夢裡的這一點看來
probably means your heart hasn't processed it yet.
或許表示你對這件事仍然耿耿於懷
I guess so.
我想是吧
You may be right.
你說的或許有理
But...
但是...
That's not all... There's something else.
不只如此,還有別的東西...
I feel like I'm forgetting about something more important.
我感覺自己忘了一些更重要的事
Something very important.
非常重要的事
Well, I guess it's not something
我想那不是你輕易
you can just get over that easily.
就能夠忘懷的事
But you know,
但你知道嗎?
your vendetta
這些恩怨情仇
is over now.
已經過去了
Plus, hating someone who's already dead
況且,憎恨一個死去的人
won't get you anywhere.
對你沒有任何好處
Isn't that right?
不是嗎?
Stand back, Thorfinn!
退後,托爾芬
Become a true warrior...
要成為一位真正的戰士
son of Thors...
成為托爾茲之子
I don't hate him anymore.
我再也不恨他了
That's the problem.
問題就出在這裡
Without any hatred I'm...
沒有了恨,我...
...empty.
很空虛
Hatred is what has kept me alive.
憎恨是讓我活下去的動力
I don't know anything
除了戰鬥
outside of the battlefield.
其他的事我一無所知
I don't know how to fix a simple roof.
簡單的屋頂修繕工作我也不會
I can't do anything.
我一無所長
I don't even know what I'm supposed to do.
我甚至不知道我該做什麼
I'm empty.
我很空虛
Work.
工作
Old Master!
老主人
If you have time to waste on chitchat, get some work done!
如果有時間聊天,不如多做一些事
I have more work for you to do today.
我今天還有更多的工作要給你們
Ready? Watch carefully.
準備好了嗎?仔細看
Try it. Catch ones that are worth eating.
試試看,撈一些肉多的魚
There!
那裡
What? It doesn't fan out.
奇怪了,魚網怎麼撒不開
Come on!
再加把勁
I can't eat meat right now, since it's Easter.
現在是復活節,所以我不能吃肉
Don't make me survive on wheat at this old age.
別讓我這一把老骨頭 只能靠小麥度日
Oh, that was great!
哇,看起來很不錯
No, I didn't catch a single fish.
不行,我連一條魚都沒撈到
Spin it more. Like this!
多轉幾圈,像這樣
Like this!
像這樣轉
Don't throw it into the same area over and over again.
別老是在同一個地方撒網
Yes.
好
It's not too late to start learning things
學習新事物永遠不嫌晚
one by one.
一點一滴慢慢累積
If you're empty, you have room to put anything inside.
如果你很空虛 表示你有很多空間可裝東西
If you're thinking about starting a new life,
如果你想要展開一段新生活
it's actually better to be empty.
從空蕩蕩的開始反而比較好
- What? You were eavesdropping? - It was loud enough to hear.
-什麼?你在偷聽? -是你們講話太大聲
Do you think I can start a new life?
你認為我能夠展開一段新生活嗎?
Get to work. I don't see your hands moving.
快點工作,我沒看到你的手在動
Man, it's freezing!
天啊,冷死人了
It's going to snow for sure!
鐵定會下雪
Fishing in this cold is going to be tough.
在這麼冷的天氣裡捕魚會很辛苦
Although, I do want to redeem myself.
是說,我的確很想扳回顏面
After all, the two of us were only able to catch
畢竟我們兩個只抓到了
three small fish and a bunch of shellfish.
三條小魚和一堆貝類
Right, Thorfinn?
對吧,托爾芬?
Huh? Oh, sorry.
你說什麼?呃...抱歉
I wasn't listening.
我沒在聽你說話
Jeez, were you deep in thought again?
天啊,你又陷入沉思了嗎?
Can humans change?
人...會改變嗎?
How can we change?
我們要怎麼改變?
Hey, Thorfinn...
喂,托爾芬
You used to be a warrior, right?
你曾是一位戰士,對吧?
Huh? Yeah.
嗯?對呀
Warriors are people who
戰士是一群拿著斧頭
hold axes, go to war, pillage, drink alcohol,
上戰場、打家劫舍、喝酒的人
and don't give a damn about anything!
對什麼都滿不在乎
Right?
對吧?
Well, I guess that sounds about right.
呃...是吧,我想你說的對
I didn't use an axe though.
但是我從沒用過斧頭
With the way you are right now,
你現在這個樣子
not a single person will think you used to be a warrior.
不會有任何人認為你曾是一名戰士
You think so?
你這麼想嗎?
What do you mean, "You think so?"
“你這麼想嗎?”是什麼意思?
Look at your reflection on the water
去看看你的水中倒影吧
and take a good look at your face.
把自己的臉看個清楚
I am honestly glad that I didn't meet you
我打從心底感到慶幸我不是在
when you were a warrior.
你當戰士的時候認識你
Worst-case scenario, I may have been killed by you.
最糟糕的狀況很有可能是我被你殺了
Humans can change, Thorfinn.
人可以改變,托爾芬
I think you are
我認為你現在
currently in the process of changing for the better.
正慢慢地變成一個更好的人
You think so?
你這麼認為嗎?
Yes.
對
Thank you, Einar.
謝謝你,埃納爾
What's wrong? Einar?
怎麼了,埃納爾?
The wheat!
小麥!
All of it...
全部都...
Did someone do this?
是人為的嗎?
Why?
為什麼?
Wheat is a strong plant.
小麥是很強韌的植物
Even if it's bent a little by wind,
哪怕被風吹彎一點
it can get back up on its own.
它也能夠自行恢復
They knew that very well.
他們很清楚這一點
They dug them out from the roots.
他們將小麥連根拔起
- Hey, where are you...? - The farmhands.
-嘿,你要去哪... -農場幫手
They're the only ones who would do this.
做得出這種事的只有他們
Wait, what are you going to do? Einar!
等等,你想幹嘛?埃納爾
Don't you know?
你不知道嗎?
If a slave uses violence against a free man...
奴隸如果對自由的人暴力相向...
I don't care. I'll kill them.
我管不了這麼多,我要殺了他們
Calm down! We don't have proof that they did it.
冷靜,我們無法證明是他們做的
Even if we confront them, they'll deny it.
就算去找他們對質,他們大可否認
Stop, Einar.
別衝動,埃納爾
Let's talk to Pater first--
我們先去找帕特...
You're so level-headed, Thorfinn.
你太冷靜了,托爾芬
Don't you understand the situation?
你還不明白現在的狀況嗎?
We used the nutrients in the soil but have zero harvest.
我們用掉了土壤的養份 卻不會有收成
We have to borrow seeds again next time.
我們下一次又得再向別人借種子
But more than that,
但更重要的是...
they... they...
他們...
should know the hardships and the joy
他們應該很清楚種麥的
of growing wheat.
辛苦和喜悅
They're farmers as well!
他們也是農夫
How could they do this...?
怎麼能夠做出這種事?
Be angry, Thorfinn.
生氣吧,托爾芬
Our wheat has been destroyed!
我們的小麥被毀了
I...
一直以來...
I have always been
我就是那個
the one doing the robbing and destroying.
搶劫和破壞的人
Unlike you,
我跟你不一樣
I don't have the right to get mad
我沒有權力
at the farmhands.
對農場幫手生氣
If you are
如果你要
going to kill the farmhands,
殺了那些農場工人
I deserve to be
我就該讓你
killed by you at least 100 times.
殺我至少一百次
First, please calm down.
請你先冷靜下來
Please.
拜託你
Einar...
埃納爾
I see.
我明白了
This is very horrible, indeed.
這的確非常糟糕
Neither of you
你們兩個
saw anyone in the act of destroying it, right?
都沒見到有人毀了這些小麥嗎?
That's right.
沒錯
Leave this the way it is
在我們結束調查之前
until we finish investigating.
先維持原樣
There might be some clues left behind.
裡面可能會有一些線索
So, do you have any guesses as to who the culprit is?
你們覺得肇事者會是誰呢?
The farmhands.
農場幫手
I see.
了解
All right, I will report everything to the master.
好的,我會向主人報告這一切
Leave the rest to me.
接下來就交給我處理吧
Back when I was a slave,
我還是奴隸的時候
I also went through horrible experiences.
也有過慘痛的經歷
I used to think,
我之前常在想
"Why do these people torment me
“為什麼這些人要做出這種
when it doesn't benefit them in any way?"
損人不利己的事呢?”
Wherever you go, there are people who like to discriminate.
不論你去到何處 總會遇到習慣歧視別人的人
But there are also people who don't.
但不是每個人都這樣
Don't lose heart, both of you.
你們兩個別灰心
About Arnheid...
關於阿奴納...
Apparently, the master is very attached to her.
主人顯然非常喜歡她
Depending on how hard we work, we can be freed,
我們是否能夠重獲自由 端看我們努力的程度
but she wasn't offered that kind of contract.
但她並沒有這種待遇
It seemed
看起來...
like she had given up on becoming free.
她似乎已經放棄追尋自由了
When you're favored, you become chained.
當你受寵的時候,便會被束縛
When you're hated, you get treated like this.
當別人看你不順眼的時候 就會有這種下場
What kind of...
這到底算是
life is this?
什麼樣的人生?
I didn't expect it to be so much work.
我沒料到工作量這麼大
- I'm exhausted! - What are you saying?
-我快累死了 -你說什麼?
- You were just watching. - Yeah!
-你只是在旁邊看而已 -對呀
Let's take another route, Einar.
我們走別條路好了,埃納爾
You're always like that.
你每次都這樣
Stop it, Einar!
別這樣,埃納爾
There's no reason for us to shy away.
我們沒必要躲開
Oh, speak of the devil.
噢,說曹操曹操就到
Hey, what's up? Why the long face?
喂,怎麼了嗎?幹嘛拉長著一張臉?
Keep your cool, Einar. Just ignore them.
保持冷靜,埃納爾,別理他們
What? Get out of the way.
是怎樣?別擋路
It was you who destroyed our field, wasn't it?
是你毀了我們的田地,對不對?
Huh? Field?
什麼?田地?
I don't know what you're talking about.
我聽不懂你在說什麼
- Einar! - Oh, I see.
-埃納爾 -是喔...
Your field was destroyed, huh?
你的田地被毀了?
That's too bad!
太悲慘了
But don't be too sad about it.
但也不用太難過啦
The wheat was made by slaves, anyway.
畢竟是奴隸種出來的小麥
No one would eat something so smelly!
不會有人想吃這麼臭的東西
Damn...
該死...
I think his jaw is broken.
我想他的下巴斷了
That was an awesome punch!
那一拳打得太好了
- You brat! - How dare you, slave!
-你這個臭小子 -你這個奴隸,好大的膽子
I'll kill you!
我要殺了你
Slave this, slave that... I've had enough!
一直奴隸奴隸地說個不停,我受夠了
Stop squealing and bring it on!
別只會動口不動手,來呀
Idiot! Don't do anything--
笨蛋,別做傻事
Thorfinn! Are you okay?
托爾芬,你還好嗎?
Let go of me!
放開我
- Take this! - You little...
-吃我一腳 -你這個小...
Damn it!
該死
Stop...
住手
What? You...
奇怪了...你...
Why...
為什麼...
F... Father?
父親?
Father is saying something...
父親在說些什麼呢?
Oh no...
完了
I'm... falling...
我掉下去了...
"Oath."
誓言
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯:歐德慧